this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello everyone this is Felina
for software engineering radio today on
the show I have Clara League West Clare
is an associate professor at Carnegie
Mellon where she works from a flight
program analysis and program repair she
holds a bachelor's degree from Harvard
and a PhD from the University of
Virginia before grad schools who spent
some time in industry at IBM where she
specialized in XML processing Claire
welcome to the show hi Felicia thanks so
much for having me so today we're going
to talk about automatic program repair
which is a pretty interesting topic but
something not everyone might be familiar
with so Claire can you take us through
the basics
what is program repair so that's a great
question Felina at a high level the idea
is that you're a developer and you're
working on code and you have a bug and
there are many different ways we might
say that we have a bug for example and I
think a very common circumstance is that
you have a regression test that fails or
maybe you write a new test and it also
fails it doesn't give you the answer you
expect research and automatic program
repair tries to come up with ways to
automatically take for example that
failing test or a failing linter check
or something like that and produce a
patch for you that automatically fixes
it and so then you don't have to so to
me that sounds like debugging there is a
mistake and I just need to fix the
mistake we just had a show on debugging
actually show three six seven if people
want to listen but what is the
difference between debugging and program
repair so in debugging there's a lot of
really interesting work in debugging I
need to listen to your show and the idea
there is to really help the developer a
little bit more interactively so
debugging techniques are going to point
out to the developer where the problem
might be to help her manually construct
her own patch where's the idea an
automated program repair is
to really remove that last step so the
developer doesn't have to spend time
tracking down or trying to understand or
putting the pieces together instead you
can imagine it's almost the creation of
an automated pull request you have a bug
and then you come back in some amount of
time and the pull request has been
created to fix that bug for you and you
don't have to and the techniques can be
related because sometimes you can look
at a patch for a bug and it helps you
understand it and in current though
there are a few deployments of program
repair and that's really how it's used
the developers are still reviewing the
patches before they're deployed and so I
think there's definitely a relationship
here between patch generation and
debugging but the real the idea really
is to automate a lot of that hard work
that the developer needs to do even with
hints to track down and change the code
to fix the bug so you mentioned a few
interesting things and I want to zoom in
on one you said generate patches and
that's plural so does that mean that if
you run for automated program repair
that multiple suggestions are being done
and as a developer you get to pick from
a bunch of options to decide which one
is the most preferable so that actually
really depends on the technique that
we're using there are some people who
produce some of the techniques produced
by researchers we'll do that some of my
work actually is capable of producing
multiple passages for the same bug and
then there are other techniques that
work to just simply construct one patch
and present that to the developer so it
depends a little bit on context and I
think context really matters for this
use case because although you know in
the current deployments we're seeing in
industry the use case I describe to you
is I think the most common where we have
a bug or a problem or a regression test
failure and a patch is presented the
developer to consider you can also
imagine this kind of technique being
used overnight so when you're Simmons
asleep
responding to some kind of automatically
detected vulnerability or intrusion
that's detected and then this kind of
technique can automatically fix the
problem at least until someone in the
morning can come in think about maybe
the better way to reconfigure the system
to avoid it so in that case we really
only need one patch because you need to
send the bleeding in your system so I
think there are a bunch of different
options for where this technology
you might be useful depending on kind of
the type of system you're running and
your your development and deployment
context so here also you mentioned
something interesting in the use case
you were just describing where something
is running overnight because they're
also finding the bug is being done
automatically right so the system
detects that there is a bug and
automatically comes up with a batch and
automatically deploys it until someone
is able to address the problem is that
what you were describing yes that is
that is what I was describing and so
while I would say the bug detection is
kind of a separate problem there's a lot
of research in that it's very
complementary to the kind of work that
I'm talking about that we do an
automatic program repair and in fact
some work at Facebook that they've been
discussing recently does connect
research in generating tests to find
bugs to work in generating bug fixes to
fix those bugs so even though they're
two separate problems they're very
complementary and we're seeing them
being used together to try and make
software better in practice but
typically to summarize typically you
would say that finding the bug is no
part of automatic program repair the
part that is automatic program repair is
generating solutions and then the
developer in the let's say the third
step still has to verify if these
patches are actually what they want I
mean yes I think that's a good summary I
suppose the developer doesn't have to
but in practice that's kind of the
assumed model right now that the
developer would then review it in the
same way you'd review a bug fix from a
teammate or from you know something
submitted to a bug bounty program you
know people still review patches
practically these days and then the
patches that are generated are already
tested to a certain extent because only
valid patches are being generated right
Oly patches will be generated that so
that at least make older existing test
cases pass if you never generate patches
where half of the test cases are broken
because then it's not a good path yes
exactly so we need checking the patch is
more like you do code review does this
make sense is this logical can other
people read this it's more that type of
verification than actual testing because
that should already be taken care of by
construction yes and by construction the
test
we'll pass because that's one of the
kind of key goals of these techniques
but yes it turns out and there are
usually more than one way almost always
there's more than one way that you can
fix a bug or make tests pass and so what
we see is sometimes humans will say oh
yeah that's fine but actually I would
want to fix it in a different way and
that might be because there's a
different way that's more readable that
better fits their their mental
abstraction of the system you know
there's any number of reasons you might
prefer one patch over another but there
are certain quality checks that any
program repair technique is already
doing to make sure that it's not doing
something completely disastrous so it
sounds pretty magical right oh I have a
bug in instead of programming myself I
can just have a machine do it for me can
you help us understand what type of bugs
could be fixed in theory with automatic
program repair oh that's a good question
Felina because I think as your question
implies the automatic program repair
techniques certainly can't and don't
claim to fix ever any kind of bug or any
kind of test failure you're going to run
into in practice and coming up with a
very precise answer to this question is
difficult I think we've struggled with
it sort of as a research community but I
can say that there are some kinds of
bugs that these techniques are better at
fixing than others so for example most
program repair techniques are only going
to make very short patches so only
changing a few lines of code at most
that actually helps you fix a fairly
large proportion of bugs in practice you
know even when humans fix bugs that a
large proportion of them don't require
changing you know multiple hundreds of
lines of code but it is limiting usually
the kind of bugs that these techniques
can fix are fairly local in their
effects so they only require changes to
a few lines of code these techniques are
particularly good at fixing problems
with control flow
so either bugs in the condition
statement of an if statement or even I
we've seen a bunch of these sometimes
you'll have series of if statements and
they should be else ifs so inserting and
else where it was once just a nip that
kind of control flow bug is a pretty
good target so you won't know ahead of
time and that's the real kind of the
tricky part right now is you know if you
the developer knew that what you needed
to do is move this block into an else
block then you wouldn't
right so I think kind of the imagined
use case right now is that the the
program repair technique will try and if
it succeeds all the better and if it
doesn't we kind of assume that a human
will have to reason about the problem I
think about it a little bit more deeply
than current reasoning techniques can do
automatically yeah so we cannot expect
automatic program repair to for example
come up with a new data structure to fix
a certain edge case that affects ten
different classes in in three different
files that type of repair because of the
scope and because of the number of
changes is probably unlikely but
something like changing a little bit of
control flow is something that an
algorithm can come up with
that's a awesome summary Thanks so now
on to how do we do this you already
mentioned some things that such an
algorithm can do for example move a
certain block how does this work how
does the algorithm come up with
suggestions for the patches what's
what's under the hood so there are
several different techniques that have
been proposed not just by my group but
by others as well so I can kind of give
you some hints about how some of them
work and I can start by focusing on some
some work that I know particularly well
because it's the work that I've been
doing with my group really back since my
PhD and that is to in our case we'll use
something called genetic programming to
automatically evolve bug fixes for a
particular program with a bug in it and
so what genetic programming is is it's a
technique that's inspired by biological
evolution that can involve solutions to
problems so in the case of a bug fix
what we'll have is a set of test cases
and we'll use those to evaluate the
fitness of a potential patch to the
program so the Fitness is just like
biological fitness it's your fitness for
reproduction you know the the birds with
the stronger wings and the point your
beak that are more attractive to mates
are more likely to pass on their genetic
material so in the case of a pass that
we're trying to evolve the number of
tests it leads the program to pass that
is its fitness those patches are better
and more likely to continue to evolve
towards a solution so what we do is
we'll take a program we'll do
little bit of analysis of some debugging
analysis actually probably using
techniques you discussed in your last
podcast to try and figure out where the
bug is more likely to be and then
generate a whole bunch of random patches
evaluate each of them for their
suitability for fitness and then if none
of them actually solve the problem lead
all of the tests to pass we will combine
and mutate and select and cause those
patches to reproduce to create a new
population of patches based on the old
ones and continue until we hopefully
find a patch that solves the problem so
just to summarize what you do is you
have a certain edit move a certain else
block in and that does really well that
change doesn't solve all the test cases
but let's say it fixes half of the
failing test cases and you have another
another mutation that is I did Oh change
the variable a to the variable B it also
does pretty well and then they will have
patch babies that have both of their
characteristics potentially because
there's some chance involved and then if
that does well then that goes on to
create a new population and you repeat
that process until all the best test
casts cases baddest that's a really
great summary exactly now then I'm still
wondering how you come up with the first
generation how do you kick-start this
project I understand how it works once
the ball is rolling but what are some of
the suggestions that start in the first
population so that's that's also a great
question so the what we start with is I
sort of hinted at this but it probably
got lost in them the later story about
evolution we're gonna start we're not
actually going to just randomly change
the program in in any way we're not
going to change an Open bracket to a %
right because you can make a lot of
changes to program text and most of them
are going to be extremely bad from the
purposes of being likely to fix the bug
so the first thing we're going to do is
start with the tests and do some
debugging analysis to narrow down the
slice of the program where the bug is
more likely to appear we can do this
automatically it's almost like doing
printf debugging
but it's automatic and it has slightly
better math to figure out the
probability that a location is is likely
to be the source of a bug so that's the
start and that the edits are only going
to be concentrated there and then we
really just randomly generate edits we
randomly generate these patches by
composing one or more of a subset of
edits that you might do to a program
there's been a lot of work on what those
edits should be we originally started
really by just moving blocks around so
inserting one statement and C after
another replacing a statement with
another statement or just deleting
things since we that initial work
there's been a lot of exploration of
maybe more natural things that you might
be more likely to do like insert a null
check for example or replace one method
call with another method call that uses
the same arguments these kinds of
templated things that we see that humans
do if we look at of the history of a
bunch of open source projects for
example so this isn't editing the
program to randomly change your Open
bracket to a % it's really at a kind of
a higher level of code abstraction so
these changes will almost always result
in code that compiles for example but it
can be it's really at the point that you
said that the sort of template it's you
might try at that point generating that
first population is random guided by
some probabilities and some analysis
that we do on the initial program so to
summarize that process you have
something like a database of edits that
developers often make like moving blocks
inserting new checks that exists you
know what developers more or less do and
these are things that you use as a first
population so there would mainly be
things that compile because it as you
said it does not make sense change
closing bracket to a percent symbol
because that will never compile the
edits are always bigger units that
developers might realistically also
apply yes exactly the edits are to take
into consideration the structure of code
and are really kind of inspired by the
things we might actually expect a person
to want to do to that code ok that
totally makes sense then I want to come
back a little bit to that debugging
analysis that you mentioned because you
said somehow we know what parts of the
old are more likely to contain the
issues than other parts can you explain
more about how does the code you know
how does your algorithm know what parts
of the code are more more buggy more
likely to be the source of this mistake
so in this work we're really relying on
insights from researchers who do
automated debugging research but the
idea I think is pretty intuitive to
people who've been programming if you
have a failing test case and you have
some passing test cases you're one way
you can try and understand what's
happening is just by running them and
seeing which code elements are executed
on the failing test case maybe lines 1 2
5 and line 8 are executed and then you
have a seg fault whereas on the passing
test cases maybe lines 1 through 5 are
executed and then lines 10 through 15
and so lines 10 through 15 probably
don't contain the bug they're not even
executed on the failing test case so
we're not going to try and make any
changes there we're going to set the
probability that they are modified by
the random process to zero whereas lines
1 through 5 which are executed by both
the passing and the failing test case
those might be initialization code for
example they will have a different
probability they'll have a probability
greater than zero and that line 8 that's
only executed by the failing test case
that'll also have a different
probability there's a bunch of research
in what those probabilities should be
but if you think about it that way it's
really just seeing what is executed by
which test cases and using that
information to figure out where you
should start to make changes and it's
very similar to something you might do
with a debugger stepping through an
executing test case to see what's
executed and even what the values of the
variables are and also fairly commonly
used with logging or printf debugging if
you're doing something like that just
say what's being executed when on which
test cases and that'll influence which
lines you're likely to try and change
first yeah I very much like how both
this automatic debugging you're
describing and also the automatic
program repair are very much based upon
what human developers do but
then just machines can do it quicker and
more efficiently and can combine
different things together but at its
core the processes are still very
similar to what a human yeah I think
that that's that's accurate I mean we
take a lot of inspiration for what might
make sense to do to a program from what
human developers do because they really
are kind of our gold standard right now
I do think you know machines when they
make suggestions when they evolve
solutions especially using something
like genetic programming they'll often
end up doing things that humans might
not expect and that can be informative
in its own way I think which is
interesting but yeah I mean the core
idea the hope is you know these systems
need to interact with human developers
still and hopefully for a long time you
know humans are going to continue
programming and so the idea is to really
be inspired by what they do so that
these systems can interact with the
systems that humans are interacting with
in kind of a symbiotic and cooperative
way got it so I watch the really nice
talk from you earlier as preparation for
this show we will totally link at any
show notes and in that's okay we're
talking about two big difference
approaches that exist currently the
semantics and heuristic approaches could
you take our audience through those two
approaches and what the difference and
similarities between them are absolutely
so the heuristic approach is starting
with the second thing you asked me about
that includes techniques like the one
based on genetic programming that I
described to you a few minutes ago and
it's heuristic because it's not using
any kind of formal reasoning in any
meaningful way and it's not using math
it's not using symbolic execution it's
not using symbolic analysis what we're
doing is we're executing the program
we're seeing what's run on it and we're
making these random changes in some
principled way to try and influence the
behavior in the desired way and there's
a many other techniques besides the one
I described that have this flavor maybe
it doesn't use genetic programming maybe
it uses a different kind of random
search maybe it doesn't use random
search at all but it's really using a
heuristic expansion of templates for
example to try and fix the bug so that's
one category of techniques they tend to
to work for a long time actually they
worked on larger programs then the
alternative did that's less true now but
when they were first proposed those
techniques scaled better and they
produce different kinds of patches as
compared to the semantic techniques
which I'll describe next the semantic
techniques are using more of that formal
analysis that heuristic techniques don't
use so the idea here is you're going to
execute the test cases and then if you
think because of the automated debugging
that we were talking about before that
the bug is likely to be on line five
semantic techniques will construct
basically a formal or a logical
specification of what the technique
thinks line five should be and then make
use of program synthesis to construct
code that does what it thinks the
correct thing is so the idea here is
that we're still using test cases to
narrow down the possible source of the
bug but instead of then honestly just
making random changes inspired by what
humans do and hoping it works semantic
techniques try and do some more formal
analysis and then make use of more
formal synthesis techniques to hopefully
make code that that maybe is more likely
to even be correct by construction in
some way so if you have a test case
that's failing because the unint
to a function X is two and on return it
should be four let's say instead it's
six right the test is failing because X
has the wrong value these kinds of
techniques we'll look at that function
and say well something's happening to ax
on line five but I know on line five it
starts off as two and I figured out that
after line five it needs to be four what
kind of code can we put there that would
make X four after line five it doesn't
even matter what's happening on line
five if you think about it because you
know it's really just going to be
replaced and so what these techniques
will then do is ask a formal program
synthesis method there's a whole bunch
of techniques that can do this and say
hey if I have a variable that starts off
as - what is code that could make it for
a heuristic approach would guess would
say oh maybe it's 12 maybe it's 10 on
going the right way
maybe it's 4 whereas SML
approach would calculate the difference
between four and two is two so clearly
what I need to do is add two that's the
difference between those two approaches
right yeah I think that's a good-ass a
good high level intuition so a heuristic
approach and actually many heuristic
approaches will say well I'm just going
to grab code randomly from somewhere
else in the program hopefully one of
them will set X to four and oftentimes
this actually does happen because code
is fairly patterned even within the same
program a synthesis approach will ask a
synthesizer give me code that makes X 4
and the synthesizer will will give it
back an answer maybe it'll give code
that says x equals 4 maybe it'll give
code that says x equals x times 2 you
know it depends a little bit on some of
the other constraints it includes but
that's how the synthesizer is going to
be used to replace the code on that line
to make X be what it needs to be yeah
that makes total sense thank you for
adding those examples it's always a very
good strategy for us to understand
what's going on I want to come back to
one other thing you said where you said
a heuristic approach takes edits from
other sources in the program so that we
talked about that database of this
initial generation for genetic
programming initially and there I
thought of it more as a database
database of edits that exists across all
programs but now I understand what you
mean more is local at it so for a given
code base you will look for edits that
often happen within this code base and
that would be at is that you try and you
wouldn't have access to a generic edit
database that would work on any type of
code base do I understand that correctly
I'm so it's an interesting kind of point
that you're making I think that that
highlights sort of a key thing about
these heuristic techniques and I am
summarizing a bunch of different
techniques when I do this just to be
clear the edits themselves can be
provided from basically anywhere they
can be a database taken from across a
whole bunch of programs it could be from
the local program but that's actually
less common but the thing about an edit
is that it doesn't necessarily contain
all of the code right and edit is a
change so if an edit is oh I'm going to
insert something
line five I think of the insert as the
change
but what's inserted like what code
should be put after line five or if I
want to insert a null check what should
I be null checking right like what what
am i wrapping in a null check what
object am i checking for null when I do
that the change the insert and null
check is provided in a database ahead of
time take it from a bunch of places but
the thing I actually end up checking for
know is taken from the local program
that I'm trying to fix so similarly if
I'm inserting code the idea that okay
one thing I can do is insert code that's
provided ahead of time the code that I
insert in virtually all of these
techniques is taken from somewhere else
in the same program okay so structurally
the edits can be the source of the edits
can be anything but what you're actually
going to change most likely is taken
from the same code base as what are
you're fixing the bug absolutely great
now I get it completely I want to move
on to another topic because fixing code
of course is very hard but what's also
very hard is writing proper test cases
sometimes fixing a bug involves making
changes to test code adding test code to
more deeply understand the book that
you're fixing is that something where
genetic program effect could also help
to adds test cases to fix test cases
that's an interesting question so the
kinds of techniques I described to you
they're really assuming that the test
cases are fixed the developers provided
them and we're going to assume that
they're good and that assumption can be
dangerous you know a few minutes ago we
were saying you know the patches we know
that at least they've been tested so
that part's done and and I was you know
being a little bit overly optimistic
there because there are lots of times
that tests are inadequate like you're
saying and and that's a risk in this
kind of technique and a reason why is
good for developers still to review the
patches that are produced but in terms
of helping us find new tests I'm pausing
actually Felina because there is like
very recent research
doing this looks funny ok I'll give you
a little context so the very early work
at genetic programming for program
repair there is also some work not by us
that co-evolved tests and patches yes
but it was like baby programs and like
you know in a subset of C right so like
it's and now recently people are trying
to combine test generation with program
repair in fact that's what Facebook did
so I'm just like saying these things to
work them out before I say them like on
the recording early or too small to
really be interesting interesting for
for irregular developers this is your
call really so that's a really
interesting suggestion Felina there's
been some initial work in making a
relationship between program repair and
test generation I don't think any of
it's been that I know of has been really
prepared for primetime or developer use
some of its been on smaller programs or
on subsets of proper programming
languages genetic programming and
related techniques for what we call
search based software engineering have
absolutely been used to help generate
tests separately from program repair so
if we sort of ignore the program repair
element there is quite a bit of work in
test generation and only at really some
initial movement towards combining the
two and certainly none that I know of
that's really ready for development that
uses the output of program repair to
improve the test cases in an automated
fashion now I can definitely imagine a
situation where a patch is produced
against a set of tests and although
earlier you're saying well you know we
have the test so at least we know that
the past is tested we were being a
little optimistic there are still
definitely times that patches can make
tests pass but the tests weren't
adequate there weren't enough they
didn't really fully check that a feature
was properly implemented right and so in
those circumstances I think program
repair can help developers make better
test Suites these if you look at the
patch and say wow my tests really
shouldn't have let that one pass right I
mean it's missing this important thing
then you can be inspired to add new test
cases
I don't know work that's doing that
automatically yet but I'm optimistic
that we'll get there hopefully as a
research community I think it's an
interesting synergy that can real
help drive program quality yeah so even
though it doesn't exist is definitely
something that could exist in the future
and something that researchers are
working towards a bit yeah and I do want
to be clear that the connection between
generating tests and even generating
tasks using search techniques like
genetic programming and program repair
that has been explored and is actually
in use at Facebook right now so they
have a technique that will automatically
test Android applications and find
crashes and it feeds into an automatic
program repair technique to fix those
crashes so I think that that connection
is already definitely being explored in
practice what we're missing is a
connection back right so if a program
repair technique finds a bad patch or or
you know realizes we need more tests in
some way to the best of my knowledge or
they're not talking about it there's no
feedback loop yet and it's that feedback
loop that I hear and your question that
I think sounds interesting what can we
do to make sure that automatic program
repair works on our code base so of
course you've already mentioned you
definitely need good test coverage
because if you don't have enough tests
then programming powers are not going to
find any useful patches are there other
things we can do to let's say prepare or
the code base to be as suitable as
possible to use program repair there are
definitely things that we can do in
particular it's not just the existence
of tests that's important but the
automation of tests so program repair
techniques that assume tests really need
to be able to run those tests
automatically and without human
assistance if you think about the
genetic programming technique you know
what we're doing is generating a
population of a hundred patches we need
to test all of them so really a code
base that is using continuous
integration or something similar for
regression testing that's using
automated testing and that's probably
the number one thing that is the most
important automated build as well
generally actually these days I think
anything that helps you safely test or
containerize your code is important
because if you think about what we're
doing it we're basically even with
semantic search you know we're making
kind of random changes to your code and
then running it and so being
to do that safely by carefully
constraining the code maybe running it
in docker running it in some kind of
container eyes solution that makes it a
lot easier to do that and set everything
up in a safe test harness so you're not
going to be breaking everything so
actually a lot of modern development
practices as we move towards CI and to
increase containerization and even new
micro services and deployments like that
are automatically moving those systems
to a context where program repair is is
applicable because what we really need
is the ability to automatically modify
build and test a program quickly and
efficiently and safely and a lot of
build not everybody does this obviously
but a lot of modern build context is is
kind of set up to support that and what
about specification I can imagine
especially for the semantic approaches
if you have invariants in your code they
would very much helps semantic
approaches to decide oh if you enter the
method it should be - and if you exit
the mellah - before so what should
happen in between is this and this is
specification very important or can
those type of informations also be
gathered from tasks and tests executions
Oh invariants would be wonderful if
developers are going to start adding
those kinds of assertions actually good
assertions and test cases are really
useful because they're effectively a
very similar thing right now semantic
techniques and here are six techniques
just try and infer that kind of
information from test case behavior but
any kind of additional annotation like
that would be really helpful to
constraining what the program is
supposed to do and figuring it out
because it's really a test is a fairly
blunt instrument right and so being able
to infer what X should be on line five
from a test it's a difficult problem and
we can't always succeed automatically so
any kind of additional annotation like
that that developers can provide is
useful to basically any kind of program
repair technique it's just another way
to know what the program should be doing
and whether it's doing the right thing
and those are the two real problems
right we're trying to figure out what it
should be doing and whether this change
helps any kind of finer grained
information assertions invariants static
checkers you know anything like that is
helpful if we get book fixes for free
then maybe that kids get developer
to write assertions I dunno maybe it
sounds interesting that would be great
I do think you know we're seeing an
increasing use of other kinds of quality
checks in development practice so people
are using more static checkers and
linters automatically at commit time to
help check code quality and some of
these tools can find really semantically
meaningful bugs you know resource leaks
and the like any kind of increased use
of those kinds of tools are also helpful
because they provide an extra quality
check for changes that are made by
automated techniques there's even
research in helping those kinds of
checkers if they say hey it looks like
there might be above on line 5 to
suggest a change to fix it but so really
any kind of additional quality check
that a developer can bake into their
codebase is helpful for automatic
transformation techniques like program
repair and what else I was thinking
about issue trackers if you have an
issue tracker and you have pull requests
commits that say hey this commit
actually fixes that issue do you do it
take that into cancer did you know this
is a good edit so that we can maybe use
that in the test channel in the story in
the patched generation is that being
used at all so that's not being used
directly that I know of there may be
work that does this in patch generation
although it's really useful when
developers do that for researchers
because when we're trying to study our
techniques we have to say I come up with
a new program or pair technique one way
I evaluate it is by trying to fix the
bugs so I need some bugs and a common
way to try and find some bugs is to go
to open source projects and look for
places where people fixed bugs and so
one way honestly one place we look is in
commit messages that connect issue
trackers so the more developers do that
actually the easier it is for us to see
what kind of problems they're fixing and
help us evaluate new techniques to help
them fix it so even though I don't know
of techniques that directly use that
link to try and construct new patches we
use them in program repair research all
the time so the the more developers can
do that the more they're helping
researchers actually come up with new
and better techniques that we can then
evaluate and show are useful to you
so it's null directly useful for program
repair on their own
one codebase but in the long run it will
be useful because it will help people
like you research this and understand
what type of editor needed and improve
those algorithms right yes exactly
I don't want to preclude the possibility
that new techniques in the future or
even techniques being developed right
now will make use of those links
directly I think that's a really
interesting idea for research but
broadly the practice is really helpful
to people like me who do research on
these kinds of systems got in so you're
already mentioned briefly in the answer
to one of the previous questions these
techniques already exist here in there
right you said that oh some ideas you
can right-click hey it seems like
there's a bug here and they already
suggest fixes and this is done with
automated program repair is that correct
is that what you were saying so there
are different kinds of ways you might
see patch suggestion the the mechanism
that you're suggesting in an IDE it says
oh hey there's a possible bug here
here's a quick fix that's using a
different kind of technique than what
we've been talking about so we've been
talking about generating patches with
respect to tests your IDE isn't doing
that but it's still doing a conceptually
similar thing which is finding evidence
of a bug and then trying to fix it the
kinds of things you see in most modern
IDs are not doing I mean especially
complicated reasoning but there's a lot
of research that's happening right now
to try and make those fixes semantically
richer more meaningful more likely to be
useful you know a lot of the times those
kinds of checks will say things like oh
you know according to our style guide
this variable should be declared as
final and the suggestion will be okay
well I'll just you know automatically
insert the final keyword for you that's
not you know it's useful but it's not
really a very meaningful bug or bug fix
in the same sense that we're talking
about for the last 45 minutes
but there is additional research that's
working on making meaningful bug fixes
with respects to those kinds of warnings
that you get statically without running
the program
other work that does actually respond
directly to test cases we're beginning
to see the initial deployments in
industry settings that we know of sort
of most
pertinent ly Facebook has recently
published a couple of papers and blog
posts describing their use of test
driven program repair in their actual
continuous deployment pipeline which i
think is really exciting and are there
already any tools that developers could
download or try if they wanna give it a
go just say hey I have a bug let's try
these automatic programming for our
tools and see where where they're at if
they can do anything
it is this the place where we are
already or is it too early for that
we're somewhere in the middle there are
a number of research prototypes that are
available that can be downloaded they're
really not intended as far as I know for
deployment but you know an enterprising
engineer with the right set up for their
code base might be able to get them to
work and see what happens and I think
we'd be very interested in hearing about
that for static quick fix checking I
think a lot of those you see are a
little bit more ready for primetime in
terms of downloading and use as far as I
know I don't think that Facebook or
other industry people who are exploring
this I don't know of anybody who has
open source their tool chain that would
allow for for more immediate use for a
developer so really it's somewhere in
the middle we have a lot of research
prototypes that are more or less
readiness for use and then we know of
mature deployments but I don't know if
any of that code is accessible so the
answer is in the middle somewhere and
are there any tools that any research
prototypes that we could link to in the
show notes or that if people as you said
with the right engineering mindset if
they are interested they could try it
out yeah I'm happy to provide some of
those cool this is a question I asked on
almost all of my show so people have
listened to my shows often they might be
waiting for this
what about programming languages which
programming language is more suitable
for this approach can we say something
like this is it there a difference
between programming language in the
suitability for programming fair or
doesn't it matter that's such a great
question
because it's actually a pretty open
research question from my perspective
about which languages are better than
others for program repair all of my
initial work was done for
techniques for C and C's an interesting
language to fix bugs in because the
compiler is very permissive it'll let
you do all kinds of things so if you're
randomly making changes to C you can run
a lot of things they won't necessarily
fix the bug but you know you can
certainly try many things so in some
sense it's easy to try and repair C
programs many different edits are
possible you can try them but on the
other hand it's hard because the
compiler isn't doing much work for you
so if a language like Java has a lot
more rules about what's not allowed and
it can stop heuristic techniques from
doing stupid things like inserting code
after a throw statement for example you
shouldn't do that as silly it's not
going to fix the bug and the Java
compiler will stop you so on the one
hand there are fewer things you can try
to fix a bug but the things you try are
more likely to succeed so there's this
tension here and I don't know how far it
goes you know I don't know if very
strongly typed languages end up being
easier or harder maybe it's just too
restrictive I'm not sure we end up kind
of locked into languages a little bit by
tooling actually because you know we
basically need to be able to process the
code we need to be able to make changes
to the code we need to be able to
compile it and sort of once you've made
that set of decisions at the beginning
of a research project you had a kind of
stuck in the language so a lot of
techniques target either C or Java
because of that because kind of the
tooling lock-in but not necessarily
because the techniques themselves are
intrinsically tied to a language so to
answer the question I think it you know
some languages are probably easier to
fix than others having a compiler with
opinions is probably useful the research
community tends to kind of pick a
language and stick with it for a bit
to avoid having to redo everything from
scratch although I've seen some
promising work actually one of my
graduate students as well as some others
out of MIT on trying to relax some of
that so we can try things on multiple
languages more easily so I'm hoping as
the research community moves forward
we'll be able to answer this question
more directly by trying things on
different languages and getting a better
understanding of which languages are
more suitable for these techniques than
others yeah because I can
imagine especially for the semantic
approaches if you want to try to
understand what could I do here if you
have a statically typed language you get
more information on the type of a
variable so you know hey this should be
this whereas if everything is dynamic
and everything is at runtime it might be
a bit harder to deduce invariants and
assertions is that true or are you
saying it doesn't really matter I think
it's just different challenges because
actually the original semantic
techniques were on C and I mean C is
technically statically typed but it's
not the type system is not helping you
very much so I think the more
information does make things better but
that doesn't mean that that we can only
work on strongly typed languages and for
the most part actually the work that I
know of doesn't I mean so Java is typed
right but you know I think we're really
kind of operating between the C and the
Java space for the most part in
evaluating our prototypes and more
information is helpful but it's not a
deal breaker by any means yes so does
that mean you don't really take type
information into account that much in
generating the patches um that depends
on the technique I don't
so heuristic techniques it depends a bit
on which templates they're using so you
know it doesn't make sense to try and
null check something that's it's
impossible for it to be null for example
so there is a little bit of type
reasoning that's happening there there
has been some work in the semantic
approach that says okay you know trying
to limit the kind of code that can be
synthesized a little bit it's a very
open space you know if I say hey X
should be 4 after this line there's lots
of code that could make X 4 so in trying
to help the synthesizer we try and give
it other hints right and so some of
those hints can come in the form of type
constraints or other kinds of
constraints we learn from the code just
by looking at it so having more typing
information can depending on this
technique be helpful in constraining the
kinds of patches that are tried but I
don't want to speak broadly about every
kind of technique because there are a
bunch of different ways that this can be
done some of them use it some of them
don't
yeah so your answer is it depends yes
right exactly what about domains you
already mentioned that Facebook applies
similar techniques to Android and I can
imagine making code for mobile is
different
and from web development different from
backends are there any types of code
bases irrespective of the programming
language used for which this technique
is more suitable I think some types of
code are easier to test automatically
than others kind of incidentally and so
any code that that is testable I either
at the unit and also at the system level
in an automated fashion so front-end
development that involves a lot of GUI
testing is probably harder usually then
something in the middle that can be
where testing can be scripted and
automated in a very simple way I say
that having just said that you know
Facebook is doing testing of Android
applications as part of their program
repair work but that's because they have
a great test harness to automatically
test Android apps right so if you have
one of those for your for your GUI then
it would work too fine it's really
dictated more by sort of quality of the
tool chain with respects to build and
test than it is the actual I think
program domain are there on the other
types of programs in the broadest sense
imaginable that this technique would
work best on any any ways of programming
such that it would be more suitable for
example if you use a huge reactive
programming is that better or worse or
it makes so different I think the short
answer is that we don't know I think
that that's a question that researchers
you know we're trying to grapple with a
little bit what kinds of bugs are these
techniques good for can we know ahead of
time that these techniques would be well
suited and I think the type of
programming is a question I don't know
that we've tried to answer but I really
think we should I like talking with you
Felina because it gives me ideas about
questions that we really need to start
exploring as a community we'll have to
acknowledge it seems like all of the
questions I ask oh is this possible but
what about this is like oh we don't know
there's so much more research to be done
it's good it's a fairly new research
area if you think about it I mean we've
only been as a community really working
on it for the last 10 years or so I mean
10 maybe you know there's some work
before that it's ok I want to be a bit
more fair the kind of repair I've been
talking about with you is fairly general
we're looking at sort of general tasks
cases and trying to change the source
code
general ways to fix them with the idea
of kind of interacting with the standard
development cycle but that works really
exists it's the last 10 ish years or so
and we still have a million open
questions as you've probably noticed
throughout this conversation there is a
fair bit of work before this general
approach that looked at particular kinds
of bugs and tried to preclude them
either by making changes to source or at
runtime so lots of cool systems for you
know can I make it impossible for buffer
overruns to happen can I make control
hijacking attacks impossible in a system
the real difference in the work is that
we're trying to work on more general
bugs that developers might encounter
generally which means questions about
what kinds of bugs what kinds of systems
what kinds of languages you know for a
long time we were just like can we do
this at all and now I think we're
beginning to grapple with these
questions about you know when can we do
this when is it suitable when does it
work fast and so on yeah and I think
it's just really interesting for our
audience to understand where are we now
what techniques can already be used in
practice and where is this field going
so I have one more of those type of
questions for you is this possible
question sure because I wonder about
pooling Google code bases which now is
maybe almost all code bases if you have
a web application you have some
JavaScript and some HTML and some CSS
and maybe likely involving a bug would
involve fixing all of these or you need
to evolve your Java code but also your
sequel code because there was a mistake
in a query and also in the handling of
the results of the query is this is
coevolution patch generation for
different type of programming languages
within code base is this something that
these approaches can handle because I
can imagine talking about human edits as
we were talking about before this is a
human edit often if I make a change I do
make a change to multiple programming
languages within one code base so I
think that's a really interesting
direction although I think we have we
have more immediate problems to solve
first so if you remember you asked me
awhile ago now which kinds of bugs these
techniques are suitable for and I said
fairly local bugs and so I think I love
the idea of polyglot repair but I think
problem one is to work on better
techniques for multi-location sort of
intertwined repairs at multiple places
in the source code at that point you
know what we need is tooling to modify
more than one language at a time and I
think there's research that's going to
help us there but I actually think
problem one is more complicated bugs
with changes in more than one place and
then we can start to worry about okay
more than one place as well as more than
one language yeah got it I want to come
back to something you said all the way
back in the beginning of the interview
but I wrote it down there's like oh if
we have time this is what I still want
to ask because at one point you said
that sometimes as a developer you can
learn from the output of patched
generation so then you're generating the
patch not necessarily to fix a bug but
also to get inspiration from hey this is
an interesting way of solving a fashion
I was wondering maybe you have an exact
read example of a case that you have
happened to you where a patch was
generated and you read it you're like oh
wow I would have never done it like this
but this is very smart could you give an
example of that um this is a really
great question because this has happened
to me a fair bit and I don't know if I
have a good concrete example I'll say
first actually I think that that this
use case is an important one
actually I've discussed with people in
industry and I've had you know
vice-president say to me you know look I
don't even care if it's right can you
just give us some existence to get us
started which I thought was kind of a
cool question I was like yeah I can do
that that's you know we can definitely
start there so I don't know if I have a
good concrete code example but one
system that I spent a lot of time
staring at was the PHP interpreter
because the PHP developers have actually
very good discipline about filing issues
and linking commits to the issues that
they close and committing regression
tests with those commits which makes it
as I sort of suggested some time ago in
this conversation a really great system
to study as a person who does program
repair because you can look back and
really get a good sense of what bugs
they're fixing what tests test them and
what the bug fixes look like but your
PHP is a really dynamic language and so
trying to understand bugs in PHP can be
very difficult
because they're all things like well if
I call string that substring and the
second argument is an 8-bit array of
characters and the first argument is a
floating-point number then it crashes
you know I'm like exaggerating but like
it feels to me like all of the bugs in
PHP are like this and so trying to
understand what the PHP interpreter is
supposed to do with all of these strange
unusual inputs is really hard you look
at the test cases and it's this PHP code
and you're just like and it's really not
until I start looking at patches and I
see okay this patch is weird oh but I
see what they actually the behavior is
supposed to be you know it's kind of
like it's an interesting way to explore
a new system especially a complicated
system with weird semantics like the PHP
interpreter is to see what changes cause
test cases to pass and fail so I have a
much better appreciation for the
internals especially if string
processing in PHP than I did before I
started doing this work now I very much
like that as a use case and I can
totally imagine that people would be
interesting our audience would be
interested in not necessarily trying
these tools to generate real patches but
exactly the case you were describing
like I have no clue where to look just
let me see some patches then at least I
can get inspired so I can see how that
in a sense it's a lesser goal to achieve
because it's way harder to generate a
real patch then to generate some things
that might be sensible but I can see how
even though it seems like you mean your
goal it could also be a very worthwhile
use case where just as a means of
inspiration you would look at some
patches I really like your idea of using
this also as a way to learn about a new
system rather than really using it to
fix it but yeah I think that's an
interesting certainly I don't want to
just call it intermediate but it's one
of those things that can have an
intermediate stepping stone that maybe
we can make development better as we are
working towards the goal of the magic as
you asked me about at the beginning you
know I think that research can be
incremental and can be incrementally
useful right and there's nothing wrong
with that I've actually had developers
say to me oh can you just tell us what
code we can delete you know because they
have these big complicated systems that
have been evolving for years and
test cases like we don't even know can
you just and this is not a question
about dead code right there's plenty of
code that is not formally dead and you
don't actually need and so if developers
have said to me look this sounds great
but honestly can you just tell us what
we can get rid of and honestly yes right
if you give me a set of tests and say
what can we delete to make these tests
still pass you know we can answer that
so we talked about many things about
generating fetches how there are
different approaches to automatically
generate batches as long as you have
proper test cases in your codebase I
have nothing more to ask but I just
wanted to give you the opportunity to
add something you think we might have
missed in this interview well I'm always
interested in hearing from developers if
they have ideas about how we can improve
their lives or their workflow so I
really encourage your listeners to reach
out you know I'm on Twitter so shout at
me about you know how your bug fixing
workflow you know what kind of problems
you have in your codebase things that
you think you want a researcher to think
about to make your life better in the
long run I mean I'd be really interested
I also want to say that if any
developers out there are thinking
wondering about a PhD and thinking hey
this sounds really fun my PhD program at
Carnegie Mellon in software engineering
we're actually particularly interested
in people with experience and so again I
encourage you to check that out because
if it's something you're thinking about
we are always interested in students who
are coming back from industry who can
really bring their perspective to the
software engineering research enterprise
it helps keep us connected to actual
practice so that's two things I think
I'd love your listeners too if they have
any problems they want us to think about
or if they're interested in tackling
research themselves I really encourage
them to reach out because we're always
interested in hearing that kind of input
and feedback in conversation so we'll
make sure that links to degrading email
in grad school project program and also
a link to your contact information is in
the show know that if listeners are
interested they can get in touch with
you anything else we truly show notes
I says they just shout at me over social
medias anything else to link to in the
show notes well I think you know there
are a couple of papers I think that are
accessible that we can link to you
mentioned a talk that I gave
and I actually think that was for a sort
of half-and-half industrial research
audience so if people want more details
of technical details about how these
techniques work that might be a good
resource and then I think we also said
I'll just throw some links up to the git
repository for existing research
prototypes for your sort of enterprising
listeners who want to play with them as
well as we have a good bibliography
actually online that we maintain so if
someone wants to take a deep dive on the
literature we can provide that link as
well great well that's it from my part
thank you so much Clara for being on the
show thanks for having me flea no this
has been really fun thanks for listening
to se radio an educational program
brought to you by Triple E software
magazine for more about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website at se - Radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at SC radio.com
you can also email us at team @ SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
se Radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening